aimaina hyouden koshiraete hitatteru no
I create a vague critical biography and wallow in it
seisei saisai nani o mada matteru no
Generation after generation, time after time,
what are you still waiting for
itsunomanika hitori ni natta
I was all alone before I knew it
tameiki hitotsu haite nageite
Breathed out a single sigh and lamented
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosunda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
en de tsunagareba kono hibi mo
Bind these days with bonds and perhaps
suteru hodo koware tenaidarou
They can be salvaged
ayumi o tomenaide
Don't stop walking forward
kibou o sutenaide
Don't give up hope
douka furimuite
Please look back
dou ka kimiyo
Please, if you would
jin jin kokoro ga itamunara
If the heart throbs with pain
kannen no ori o uchiyaburu nda
Break through the ideology that imprisons you
enen tsukihi wa megurukedo
Time goes around for eternity
suteru ni wa yami ga asaidarou
But the darkness within you is still shallow,
not worth throwing it all away
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosu nda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
ai o wakeaeba kono hibi mo
If we love each other then surely these days will
mouichido kimi o terasudarou
Once again, shine upon you
Hagoromo and Hamura
Mother loved this world.
She tried to love humans.
But her wish was dashed
so she ate the fruit of the Divine Tree
to try to protect her children.
(ゼツ)母は この地を愛した。
そして人間を愛そうとした。
However...
Mother's real tale of despair
begins from here...
だが その希望は奪われ→
自らの子を守るために
神樹の実を口にした。
Shortly afterwards,
Mother gave birth to twins.
しかしだ…。
母の本当の絶望の物語は
ここから始まる。
They were... Hagoromo and Hamura.
母は それから間もなく
双子を産んだ。
それが ハゴロモとハムラだ。
Mother looks up at the sky
like that every day...
I wonder what she's looking for?
She never tells us anything.
No one knows what's in her heart.
(ハムラ)母上は ああして
毎日 空を見上げているが→
いったい何を見ているのだろう。
Perhaps she has feelings that even we,
her own sons, cannot fathom.
(ハゴロモ)私たちには
何も語ってくれないからな。
心の内は誰もわからない。
きっと母上には→
我ら息子とて計り知れない思いが
あるのかもしれぬな。
Hey, Hagoromo and Hamura!
Please come with me!
What's the matter, Haori?
If you use all the water at your place,
(ハオリ)
ねぇ ハゴロモ ハムラ ちょっと来て！
there won't be any water
downstream for the rice paddies.
どうした ハオリ？
That's not my fault!
Wait!
What's going on?
てめえのところで
全部 水をとっちまったんじゃ→
I'll tell ya what's going on!
This guy is taking all the water!
下流の田んぼにゃあ
水はいかなくなっちまうだろ！
それは俺のせいじゃねえ！
My paddy's upstream,
so I can't help it!
待てよ どうしたんだ？
But until now, wasn't there
enough water for everyone?
どうもこうも こいつが
水を全部とっちまうからよ。
Well, all of a sudden,
the flow of the river's gotten weak.
俺の田んぼが上流にあるんだから
当たり前だろう。
だけど 今までは他のところにも
水はいってたんだろ？
それが
急に川の流れが弱くなってよ。
Did something happen upstream?
I would go and check,
but there's a huge bear
roaming around this mountain.
You gotta be really careful.
上流で何かあったのか？
Just recently, an old lady went
foraging for edible wild plants,
and got hurt really bad.
上流を見にいくにも
この山には→
All right. We'll go check.
どでかい熊がウロウロしてて
うかつには入れねえ。
Really? That'd be great!
この前だって
山菜採りに入った ばあさんが→
Be careful, Hagoromo.
We'll be fine.
大ケガさせられたしよ。
Let's go, Hamura.
わかった 我々で見てくる。
Right.
ほんとか？ 助かるよ。
気をつけてね ハゴロモ。
See anything?
Hold on a minute.
大丈夫だ。 行くぞ ハムラ。
うん。
There's a huge boulder upstream.
何か見えるか？
ちょっと待って。
(ハムラ)どうやら上流に
でかい岩があるね。
I see...
So this is what's blocking
the flow of the river.
But where did this boulder
come from?
It wasn't there the last time
we were up here.
なるほど こいつが川の流れを
ふさいでたのか。
Either it fell from somewhere,
or someone put it there.
だけど
この岩は どこから来たんだ？
What do you bean by "someone"?
No one can move a boulder this big
前に来たときには なかったよ。
other than Mother and you,
Elder Brother.
どこからか降ってきたか
誰かが置いたか。
I put it there.
誰かって…
こんな大岩を動かせるのは→
Hey, don't brush me off
like I'm some sort of bug...
母上か兄者以外いないぞ。
‘Cuz I'm not a bug...
(ガマ丸)
それは わしが置いたのじゃ。
I'm a toad.
(ガマ丸)お～い 無視するな。
Hey, am I going crazy?
じゃが
わしは虫ではなく 蛙じゃがな。
There's a toad trying to
make bad jokes...
Well, Elder Brother,
it must mean I'm going crazy too.
おい 私の頭がおかしいのか？
No, you're not going crazy.
I really am talking to you.
蛙が つまらぬシャレを言っている。
兄者… それなら俺も
頭がおかしくなったってことか？
But if you think my jokes aren't funny,
then that's a little crazy.
べつに お前たちの頭は
どうにもなっとらん。
ちゃんと わしが話してるんじゃ。
いや… わしのシャレが
おもしろくないという点で→
No one's hiding around here...
It's not some
Ventriloquism Jutsu either.
おかしいかもしれぬが。
You're pretty wary for a human.
You're pretty arrogant for a toad.
(ハムラ)誰も隠れてない。
We toads have lived here
far longer than you.
腹話術じゃないみたいだ。
You just don't know it.
用心深いやつじゃの
人間の分際で。
A talking toad...
ずいぶんと威張った蛙だな。
You think people will be happy
if we captured it and took it home?
Fool!
お前たちが知らないだけで
わしら蛙のほうが→
Do you really think you both
can catch me?
ずっと昔から
この地に住んどるんじゃ。
For a toad, you sure talk big...
しゃべる蛙って捕まえて帰ったら
みんな喜ぶかな？
It seems we have a guest.
バカ者！ 貴様ら程度に捕まる
わしではない！
言うじゃないか 蛙のくせに。
おっ どうやら
新しいお客さんじゃぞ。
That's a huge bear!
グォ～ッ！
Perfect timing.
I'll show you just how strong I am.
グォ～ グォ～！
グォ～！
でかい熊だな。
ちょうどいい。
わしの強さを自慢してやる。
I placed this boulder here
so I could meet you two.
(ハムラ/ハゴロモ)おぉ～。
My name is Gamamaru.
And you two are Hagoromo
and Hamura, right?
A toad just addressed us
by our first names...
この岩はお前たちに会うために
わしが置いたのじゃ。
Come with me, you two.
わしの名前は ガマ丸。
お前たちは ハゴロモとハムラじゃな。
Oops, I almost forgot.
蛙に呼び捨てにされた。
２人とも ちょっと来い。
Oh...
Not bad.
おっと 忘れてた。
ほぅ… 少しはやるようじゃな。
Why did you bring us here?
Do you know what that is?
Of course.
That's the Peak of Demise.
なんだ？
こんな場所に連れてきて。
Have you ever seen
what's beyond that?
あれを知っているか？
No, never.
Mother has warned us
not to go near that peak.
もちろん。
あれは 終焉の峠。
Everyone must follow that law.
あの向こうを見たことはあるか？
No one has ever seen
what's on the other side.
いいや ないな。
The truth behind the Divine Tree
is beyond that peak.
母上からあの峠には近づくな
と言われている。
The truth behind the Divine Tree?
全員の掟だ。
The Divine Tree has been
absorbing the power of this land.
誰もあの向こう側を
見た者はいない。
As long as that tree exists,
the land will continue to weaken.
あの向こうに神樹の正体がある。
神樹の正体？
Is that true?
But I've heard that it's because of
the power of the Divine Tree
(ガマ丸)神樹は大地の力を
吸い取り続けている。
that this land has thrived.
あれがあるかぎり
この大地は弱り続ける。
You're wrong!
If you want to know the truth,
go see what's on the other side
of that peak.
そうなの？ でも神樹の力で
この地は潤っていると聞くけど。
Later!
違う。 真実を知りたかったら
峠の向こうを見てみるんじゃな。
"The truth"?
じゃあの。
Is Lady Kaguya really not here?
真実。
How many times must I tell you?
She's not here.
Welcome home,
Masters Hagoromo and Hamura.
はぁ？
ほんとにカグヤ様はいないのか？
What's the matter?
This man is very persistent.
何度言われても
いないものはいません。
Who are you?
I'm a traveling medicine peddler.
おかえりなさいまし
ハゴロモ様 ハムラ様。
I wanted to do some business here
どうした？
このお方がどうにもしつこくて。
and came to get
Lady Kaguya's permission.
あんた誰？
オイラは旅の薬売りだ。
Where is Mother?
She said she would be away tonight.
この辺で商売しようと思って
カグヤ様の許可をもらいに来たのよ。
I see, so she's gone out again.
She's been away a lot lately.
What do I do now?
母上は？
今晩は留守にされると。
そうか また出かけたのか。
Well now, what do you have here?
Let me take a look
at your medicines.
最近は多いな。
まいったな。
What are you doing to
my products?!
ほぅ… どれどれ？
俺がお前の薬を見てやる。
These are just weeds
and moldy nuts...
This one's a poisonous mushroom.
If you take these,
you'll get even sicker.
うわぁ 人の商売道具に
なにしやがる！
You're just a snake oil salesman...
ただの雑草にカビの生えた木の実。
こりゃ毒キノコだ。
This village has our mother,
my elder brother and me.
こんなの飲まされたら
よけい具合が悪くなる。
We can cure any illness anywhere,
at anytime.
さてはお前 ペテンの薬売りだな？
ギクッ！
No one will buy stuff like this.
この村には母上と兄者の力がある。
Your power...
Is it from the Divine Tree?
それがあれば どんな病気だって
たちどころに治る。
Just get out of here...
or you'll be sorry.
こんなの買うやつは誰もいないよ。
それって あの神樹様の
お力なのか？
いいから とっとと出ていけ。
痛い目に遭いたくなきゃな！
Damn it!
How dare they belittle me!
あ… あ… あぁ～！
They made me so mad,
my back pain is flaring up again.
チクショー！ バカにしやがって…。
The Divine Tree, huh?
アタタタタ…。
If I take even just a small branch,
I could sell it for a fortune...
頭にきたら
腰の痛みが ぶり返してきたぜ。
Yes! While the devil is away...
Just forget about it.
神樹か…。
Don't be foolish enough
to go near the Divine Tree. You'll die.
もし 欠片でも持って帰れば
さぞ お高く…。
You are—!
I apologize for earlier.
よし！ 鬼のいぬ間に…。
My younger brother
is quite hot-tempered.
やめろ やめろ！
うかつに神樹に近づくと 死ぬぞ。
What do you want?!
Oww!
あっ！ お前は…。
I want to ask you something.
さっきは悪かったな。
弟は ちゃめっ気があるんでな。
Are you joking?!
You're not getting
anything out of me!
If you answer me,
I'll heal your back.
何の用だ… あっ！ イテテテ…。
お前に聞きたいことがある。
Like doing that will cure anything.
ふざけるな!!
何も教えてやるものか！
If it's that simple,
no one would go through...
What? The pain's gone?!
答えてくれれば 腰を治してやる。
Hey! You really did fix my back!
フン！ そんなことで
病気が治ったら 誰も苦労は…。
So, will you answer my questions?
Yes! Anything!
あ… あれ!? 治った…。
You've traveled to
many different places, correct?
おぉ～！ 本当に治ってる。 ハハハ!!
Oh, yes.
That's how I make my living.
で… 私の質問に答えてくれるか？
へい！ なんでも。
Have you ever seen
what's beyond that peak?
お前は いろいろな場所を
旅してるのだろ？
No, I haven't.
But I've seen many other lands...
えぇ そりゃ もう。
それが商売ですから。
What do they say about
my mother in other lands?
あの峠の向こうは
見たことがあるか？
Well, that's... um...
Tell me even if
it's something negative.
あぁ いえ それはないですが
他のところなら…。
Okay.
そこでの母上の噂は どんなだ？
There are rumors about people
rebelling here and there,
へい そりゃ… あぁ え～っと…。
over Lady Kaguya's
Ritual of the Divine Tree.
言いづらいことでもいい。
へい…。
And in order to suppress them,
実は カグヤ様が行ってる
神樹へのしきたりに反対して→
Lady Kaguya has
annihilated the instigators.
Lately, rumors are swirling that
Lady Kaguya is just a tyrant...
あちこちで
反乱が起きてるって噂です。
それを鎮圧するのに カグヤ様は→
"Annihilated"?
彼の国の連中を
全滅させているとか…。
No wonder Mother has been
away a lot...
最近じゃ カグヤ様は暴君だって噂が
あちこちで…。
Leave, and never return.
It's for your own good.
全滅…。
Yes, sir!
それで 母上は 最近 留守に…。
行け！ もう 戻ってくるな。
そのほうが お前のためだ。
へい。
Everything is going well.
Elder Brother?
Hmm?
Oh good, no news is good news.
Elder Brother, are you still thinking
about what that toad said?
どこも異常ないよ。
兄者？
あ… あぁ。
No... It's not about that, but...
何もないのが いちばんだ。
兄者… あの蛙の言ったことが
気になるのかい？
They're part of the Ritual
of the Divine Tree...
いや そういうわけではないが…。
No way!
Elder Brother!
あれは 神樹様へのしきたりの…。
Haori!
Hagoromo...
Hamura...
What's going on?
あっ！ そんな…。
あ… 兄者！
I've received notice
to serve the Divine Tree.
ハオリ！
But—!
I have no choice.
ハゴロモ… ハムラ…。
これは…。
This is a ceremony that Lady Kaguya
established eons ago...
私に 神樹様への
お使いの知らせが来たの。
Hagoromo, Hamura...
だが…。
しかたないことよ。
It was only for a short time,
but I'm glad I got to meet you two.
ずっと昔から カグヤ様が決めた
しきたりなんだから…。
Please remember me.
ハゴロモ… ハムラ… 短い間だったけど
２人に会えて 楽しかったわ。
Haori!
私のこと 忘れないでね。
ハオリ！
Mother...
Please end
the Ritual of the Divine Tree.
That is not possible.
But—!
I will not tolerate any defiance,
even if you are my sons.
母上…。
神樹のしきたりを
中止してください。
Then please tell me...
What happens to those who go to
the Divine Tree as part of this ritual?
(カグヤ)それは ならぬ。
しかし…。
お前たちとて わらわに
逆らうことは許しません。
Why does no one ever return?
This ritual is necessary...
until the others arrive.
では 教えてください。
あのしきたりで
神樹に向かった者たちは→
"The others"?
どうなるのです？ なぜ
１人も帰ってこないのですか？
You don't need to know
about them just yet.
しきたりは必要なのだ。
あの者たちが来るまでは。
Hagoromo, Hamura...
I am leaving once more.
あの者たち？
それはまだ
お前たちが知る必要はない。
Take care of things in my absence.
Yes.
ハゴロモ ハムラ わらわはまた出かける。
Elder Brother...
You're not thinking of...
留守を頼む。
はい。
Yes, I intend to climb that peak.
If Mother finds out, you'll get
into a great deal of trouble.
I'm prepared for the consequences.
兄者 まさか…。
Okay, Elder Brother.
I'm coming with you.
ああ 私はあの峠に登ろうと思う。
母上に知れれば
ただでは済まないぞ。
それは覚悟のうえだ。
わかった 兄者 俺も行こう。
What is this?!
Elder Brother!
Hamura!
何だ これは？
兄者！
ハムラ。
What's wrong?
Elder Brother!
Can you deal with this cocoon?
Haori!
どうした？
兄者 この繭を。
Haori! Wake up, Haori!
Elder Brother...
It's no use...
ハオリ！
She's dead.
ハオリ 起きろ ハオリ。
兄者 ムダだ。
So this is... the truth behind
the Ritual of the Divine Tree.
死んでる。
うぉ～ うぉ～！
Elder Brother! Your eyes!
(ハムラ)これが
神樹のしきたりの正体。
Come out, Gamamaru!
(ハムラ)兄者 その目は…。
It seems like you went
beyond that peak...
出てこい ガマ丸。
Come with me.
どうやら行ったようじゃな
あの峠の向こうに。
Where are we?
わしに ついてこい。
This is the Land of Toads.
What is this... strange power I feel?
ここは？
Oh... I'm impressed that a human
can feel the power here.
ここは蝦蟇の国じゃ。
The natural power known as
Sage Power flows freely here.
なんだ？ 不思議な力を感じる。
And so, if you use this power...
ほう さすがじゃな
人間でここの力を感じとるとは。
Even I can do something like this.
ここは仙力と呼ばれる
自然パワーが満ちておる。
Wow...
Follow me!
だから その力を使えば…。
よっ！ わしにでも
こんなことができるのじゃ。
This is known as the Memory Stone.
すげえ。
よいしょ ついてこい。
"Memory Stone"?
Everything that occurs aboveground
is recorded in this stone...
Look at what happened in the past...
これは記憶石と呼ばれるものじゃ。
記憶石？
Long ago, that tree fell
from the sky...
地上に起きた あらゆることを
記録している石じゃ。
And, as if in pursuit, your mother
Kaguya appeared here.
見るがいい
かつて 何が起きたのかを。
その昔 あの樹は
空から降ってきた。
And when your mother arrived,
she fell in love with
the emperor of this land
それを追うように
お前たちの母 カグヤもやってきた。
and she became pregnant with you.
However,
Kaguya's destiny with humans
was to be trifled by them
カグヤは地上に降りてから
この地の帝と恋に落ち→
and in the end,
she became their enemy.
Kaguya acquired the power
of the Divine Tree,
お前たちを身ごもった。
and your father,
along with his people,
だが カグヤの運命は
人間に翻弄され→
were sacrificed to it.
そして 人間の敵に回った。
But, to make sure
mankind didn't perish,
she revived some of the humans,
カグヤは 神樹の力を得て
お前たちの父親を→
erased their memories
and put them back.
そして 人々を
神樹の生贄に変えた。
Only Kaguya knows the truth.
Where is Mother from anyway?
一部の人間は
人間を絶やさぬために→
Why does she protect
the Divine Tree?
I don't know.
記憶を抜かれ
元に戻されたようじゃがな。
Perhaps it's related to the fact that
she appeared from far up in the sky.
真相は カグヤしか知らぬ。
One thing is clear...
母上は いったいどこから？
なぜ神樹を守ろうとする？
Since the Divine Tree took root,
わからん。
遠い空からやってきたことと→
the Nature Energy of this land
is being depleted.
関係しているのかもしれぬ
はっきりしていることは…。
How could that happen?
あの神樹が生えてから→
Not just from the land...
but from humans too.
明らかに大地の自然エネルギ-は
減少しているということじゃ。
As long as that Divine Tree exists...
this great land will wither,
and we will suffer the same fate.
なんてことを。
大地ばかりではない
人間からもじゃ。
あの神樹がある限り
やがて大地は枯れ果て→
We must speak with mother.
我々も同じ運命をたどる。
Will she even listen to us?
Hagoromo,
your mother's power is immense.
母上と
話をする必要があるな。
I doubt that you can
confront her directly.
だけど母上が話なんて…。
Even if you are her son.
ハゴロモよ お前の母の力は絶大じゃ。
Gamamaru, will you teach me
how to use Sage Power?
わしも素直に話を
聞いてくれる相手とは思えない。
Elder Brother!
You're not planning to fight Mother,
are you?!
たとえ息子のお前でも。
It's just in case...
ガマ丸 私に仙力の使い方を
教えてくれないか。
I see...
If you, who inherited Kaguya's power,
acquire Sage Power...
兄者 まさか母上と
戦うつもりでは？
you could definitely take her on.
万が一のためだ。
– However...
– What is it?
なるほど カグヤの力を
強く受け継いだお前が→
Teaching you Sage Power
is very risky.
Why is that?
仙力を習得すれば たしかに
対抗できるかもしれぬ。
Is there any guarantee that
after acquiring Sage Power,
you won't become the same
as your mother?
じゃが。
なんだ？
お前に
仙力を教えることは→
Gamamaru... After coming this far,
have you become scared?
危険な賭けじゃ。
なぜだ？
What did you say?
仙力を会得したお前が→
You're contradicting yourself.
母親と同じにならない保証が
あるか？
Why did you lie in wait for us, then?
You planned to pit us against Mother
and make us fight from the very start.
ガマ丸 ここまできて→
怖気づいたのか？
なんじゃと？
お前の話は矛盾している。
You're pretty shrewd for a human,
aren't you?
お前は
なぜ私たちを待っていた？
お前は母上と我々が戦うことを
最初から予測していたはずだ。
Yes, I had a revelation.
Revelation?
Yes, a dream.
Toads rarely, if ever, dream.
う… お前 人間のクセに鋭いな。
But that dream was
more like a prophecy...
そうじゃ
お告げがあったのじゃ。
I dreamed of you battling Kaguya.
(ハゴロモ)お告げ？
夢じゃ。
ガマは滅多に夢を見ない。
How did it end?
I don't think his dream
went that far.
その夢は いわば予言に近い。
If it did,
he wouldn't be so nervous.
わしはお前たちが
カグヤと戦う夢を見た。
Wha—?! How can you see so far
into a toad's heart so clearly...
その結果は？
Just who are you?
そこまでは
見ていないはずだ。
見ていたら
びびりなどしない。
ゲコ!? 何から何まで
蛙の心を読むとは。
なんてやつじゃ。
Clear your mind...
Just feel the Nature Energy
and take it into yourself.
何も考えるな。
自然エネルギーを感じて
それを自分の中に取り込め。
He's a surprise...
Hagoromo's acquired Sage Power
in no time at all.
《こいつは驚きだのお。
ハゴロモめ あっという間に
仙力を習得しとる》
Mother!
You're back so soon...
Where is Hagoromo?
Elder Brother is still out
patrolling the village...
母上
もうお戻りになられたのですか？
Hamura!
Hiding things from me is useless.
ハゴロモは どうしたのです？
兄者は まだ村を
見回りに行ったまま。
ハムラ。
わらわに隠し事は無駄だ。
It's useless... even if you try to
repel me with your Byakugan...
My Byakugan is far more
superior to yours.
う！
無駄だ。
お前の白眼で
跳ね返そうとしても→
わらわの白眼は
お前のを はるかに上回る。
kaze ga fui te iku
The wind is blowing
yoru o mata yorokete aruku
I stagger through the night
butsukatte koron de shippai bakkashite
Colliding, falling, and failing
make sou ni naru kedo
I'm always about to lose
warawaretatte ii yo kanarazu umaku iku sa
Go ahead and laugh, I'll figure out a way
gomen ne datte ieru
I'm even willing to say I'm sorry
nakitai nakitai nakitai kurai ni
Until we feel like crying and crying
kirei na tsuki no shita uta o utaou
Let's sing a song under the pretty moonlight
donna ni kuradanai sekai datte ii yo
It doesn't matter how awful the world is
setsunai setsunai rarabai kurai ni
Like a sad, sad lullaby
mune ga kurushikute mo hecchara na no sa
even if it hurts inside, it won't bother us
naki sou naki sou naki sou na hodo
Until we're about to cry and cry
yasashii uta datte arun dakara
There will always be a gentle song
You two broke the law,
and went to the peak, didn't you?
Hiding things from me is useless.
I can read your thoughts
and feelings.
Then why?
You must know why we're
angry with you, Mother.
It seems that you were in love
with that young girl...
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
"A Fabricated Past"
Mother, even you must have
believed in that in the past!